<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Pat&#39;s Log</title>
    <link>https://patrickpt.github.io/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Pat&#39;s Log</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 21 Jun 2022 15:06:45 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://patrickpt.github.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>An introduction to ChatGPT written by ChatGPT</title>
      <link>https://patrickpt.github.io/posts/intro_chatgpt/intro_chatgpt/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jan 2023 00:55:07 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://patrickpt.github.io/posts/intro_chatgpt/intro_chatgpt/</guid>
      <description>ChatGPT: Optimizing Language Models for Dialogue What to do if you have 15Min time to spare? Feed ChatGPT with prompts to write an introductory article about ChatGPT. And I promise, this is the only part which is not based on a Large Language Model. Everything else was written by ChatGPT. For better readability I replaced the prompts with simple headers.
What is ChatGPT? Are you tired of boring, robotic chatbots that can’t hold a conversation or understand your needs?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why and how do you create your own AI blog?</title>
      <link>https://patrickpt.github.io/posts/2023_01_01_why_a_blog/why_a_blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 09:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://patrickpt.github.io/posts/2023_01_01_why_a_blog/why_a_blog/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to my blog.
Why not Medium? It is 2023 and there are plenty of easy ways to create content about ML, Data Science and AI on the internet. In fact with the accessability of platforms like Medium it is easy.
Isn&amp;rsquo;t it actually dumb to create your own blog instead of using these possibilities?
Maybe, but my purpose is not to attract as many readers as possible but to learn something and make my learnings acceptable for others as well.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
